That concludes a mammoth project.
대규모 프로젝트가 완성됐어요
Three weeks in the making.
3주나 걸렸어요
In the course of those three weeks, starting with the data curation, the working with frontier models,
그 3주 동안 데이터 큐레이션을 시작으로 프론티어 모델 작업을 하고
and then ending with the complete user interface in Gradio with even that very unnecessary but great
그라디오의 사용자 인터페이스를 완성했습니다 불필요하지만 훌륭한 플롯 3D
plot 3D chart on the bottom right, together with the trace from the agents and the results of the memory.
차트인 우측 하단에 요원의 흔적과 메모리의 결과가 포함돼 있죠
Um, and all of it came together.
모든 게 잘 맞아떨어졌어요
Remember, the user interface was not really the point.
기억하세요 사용자 인터페이스는 요점이 아니었어요
The user interface was a bit extra, so we can monitor it.
사용자 인터페이스가 좀 특이해서 비트를 모니터할 수 있어요
The main point is that that just runs and it just keeps running, and as it runs, it will be continually
중요한 건 그게 계속 실행된다는 겁니다 실행되는 동안 몇 분마다
notifying me every few minutes with a new deal that it hasn't surfaced before.
계속 제게 알려요 전에 나타나지 않은 새 계약과 함께요
And that is the conclusion of a very satisfying, great project that we have built end to end.
끝에서 끝까지 우리가 만든 아주 만족스럽고 훌륭한 프로젝트의 결말이죠
And so with that, let's take a moment to do a retro of the last eight weeks.
그럼 지난 8주간의 과거를 되짚어 보도록 하죠
One more time.
한 번 더요
I've gone on about this so many times, and so you'll be happy, or maybe a bit sad that this is the
비트코인 얘기를 정말 많이 했는데 기쁘기도 하고 슬프기도 할 거예요
final retrospective you started eight weeks ago.
8주 전에 시작한 마지막 회고니까요
Over on the left, we wanted to get to being an LM engineer, someone who had mastered LM engineering,
왼쪽에서 LM 엔지니어가 되고 싶었어요 LM 엔지니어링을 통달하고 고도로 숙련되고
highly proficient, advanced, and this is how we got there.
진보한 사람요 이렇게 된 거예요
In the first week we played with lots of models.
첫 주에는 모델들과 많이 놀았어요
We found out how many times the letter A appeared in sentences.
A가 문장에 몇 번이나 나왔는지 알아냈어요
We took a quick look at one preview amongst other things.
미리 보기와 함께 다른 것들도 살펴봤죠
In week two we first saw gradient and we played with some multi-modality, which was fun.
2주 차에는 그러데이션을 처음 접했는데 다중 모듈을 활용해서 재미있게 작업했어요
We also saw an early version of agent ization.
요원 아이즈의 초기 버전도 봤죠
In week three we got stuck into hugging face.
3주 차에는 얼굴 껴안기가 유행이었죠
We had pipelines, we had tokenizers, we had models.
파이프라인, 토큰라이저, 모델 등이 있었죠
In week four we got deeper into hugging face.
4주 차에는 얼굴을 더 많이 껴안았어요
We selected Llms, we generated code and we had that remarkable project, with the 60 000 time performance
Lms를 선택하고 코드를 생성해 놀라운 프로젝트를 진행했습니다 5주 차에 6만 시간
improvement in week five.
성능 향상을 기록했죠
We built our Rag solution for insert film, which used chroma, and also briefly we used face as well
필름 삽입용 래그 솔루션을 만들었는데 크로마를 사용했고 얼굴도 잠깐 사용했어요
and created our expert.
전문가도 만들었죠
And maybe you did the big project associated with that.
그것과 관련된 큰 프로젝트를 맡았을지도 모르죠
Week six we fine tuned a frontier model, although most of which six was spent curating data.
6주 차에는 개척 시대 모델을 미세 조정했습니다 하지만 6주 차 대부분은 데이터를 수집하느라 썼죠
But that is such an important activity.
하지만 그건 중요한 활동이잖아요
Week seven.
7주째예요
We did fine tune an open source model that then beat the frontier, and in week eight, we packaged
미개척지를 돌파한 오픈 소스 모델을 완성했고 8주 차에 유전자
it together to a genetic AI solution complete with seven agents and a user interface.
인공지능 솔루션에 7개의 에이전트와 사용자 인터페이스를 결합했죠
And it was fabulous.
정말 멋졌어요
So that was the journey.
그게 여정이었어요
I need to take a moment to thank you.
잠깐 감사의 말을 해야겠어요
Thank you so much for staying through to the end.
끝까지 함께해 줘서 고마워요
You can't, I can't I can't explain how much I appreciate it.
얼마나 감사한지 말로 다 못 해요
It's really, uh, so, so wonderful to have had people come all the way through the course, gone through
정말 멋져요 8주간의 여정을 거쳐 여기까지 온 모든 분들과 함께해서 정말 기쁩니다
the eight week journey, and take advantage of everything that we've been doing and get to this point.
우리가 해온 모든 걸 활용해서 여기까지 온 거죠 Get up
And I've, I've heard from several of you along the way, and it's been really, really rewarding for
그동안 여러 분께 이야기를 들었는데 이번 경험을 통해 정말 큰
me to experience this.
보람을 느꼈어요
Uh, super grateful.
정말 감사해요
I hope you've enjoyed it.
즐거우셨길 바라요
I obviously I've enjoyed it a lot.
물론 정말 즐거웠어요
Uh, far too much.
너무 많이요
I hope you've enjoyed it as well.
여러분도 즐거우셨길 바라요
I really hope you can stay in touch.
계속 연락하고 지냈으면 좋겠어요
By all means, please do LinkedIn with me if you're open to that.
괜찮다면 링크드인에서 저와 함께 일하세요
If you're okay with that, I'm very much welcome.
그래도 괜찮으시다면 전 환영이에요
LinkedIn connections.
링크드인 연결망요
And we can have a community, um, and message me if you've got to this point, I definitely want to
공동체를 만들 수 있어요 여기까지 오면 메시지 주세요 꼭 듣고
hear it.
싶어요
Uh, and of course, you've got this big challenge.
물론 큰 도전도 있죠
Now, can you take what you've learned and use it to build your own project?
지금까지 배운 걸 자신의 프로젝트에 활용할 수 있겠어요?
Maybe that idea I had about using the finance data would be an interesting one.
재무 자료를 이용하자는 제 아이디어가 흥미로울지도 몰라요
See if you can build something that could make some money.
돈이 될 만한 걸 만들어 봐요
If you do, then I expect a lunch out of it.
그럼 점심으로 사 주세요
At the very least, perhaps.
적어도 그럴 거예요
Uh, but that would be a fun challenge.
하지만 재미있는 도전이 될 거예요
Whatever you do with it, I want to hear about it.
그 돈으로 뭘 하든 내게도 알려줘요
If you built a great platform that is using some of this learning, then please share it.
이 학습을 이용해 훌륭한 플랫폼을 구축했다면 공유하세요
I'd love other students to see that too, and it's great to have that kind of output as a tiny little
다른 학생들도 그걸 봤으면 해요 그런 출력을 작은 엑스트라로 갖는 건 멋진 일이죠
extra.
기억하실지 모르겠지만 아주 오래전 첫째 주에 제가 마지막에
going to be a little extra juicy nugget at the very end, and this is what it is.
아주 흥미진진한 게 나올 거라고 했었죠 바로 이거예요
I wanted to tell you that I did a personal project where I fine tuned an LLM.
제가 개인적으로 LLM을 조율한 프로젝트가 있어요
It was in fact a llama two LLM from the beginning of this year, uh, on all of my text message history.
올해 초부터 문자 메시지 기록에 라마 2개의 LLM이 있었어요
It turns out that I have 240,000 text messages that have built up over time on my iPhone, uh, since
문자 메시지가 240,000개나 왔더라고요 시간이 지나면서 아이폰에 쌓인 거죠 아이폰이
I had the first iPhone some time ago.
처음 생긴 지 좀 된 후로요
And so I had a lot of text message history, and I was able to use that to train llama two to make a
문자 기록이 아주 많았는데 그걸 이용해서 라마 2를 훈련해서 제 시뮬레이션을
simulation of me.
만들었어요
Uh, and there's a write up on my website, on my blog, Edward Dot com.
제 블로그 에드워드 닷컴에도 글이 올라왔어요
You can take a look and there's instructions for how you can do it too.
어떻게 하는지도 설명서가 나와 있어요
And of course, I was using llama two and now llama 3.1 is so much better along with some of the others
라마 2에서 라마 3으로 바뀌었죠 1이 훨씬 나아요 콴 같은 다른 선수들과
like like Kwan and so on.
비교하면요
So you could definitely have a stab at this, and you will probably have even better results than I
그러니 여러분도 시도해 보세요 제가 했던 것보다 더 좋은 결과가 나올 거예요
had.
결과는 소름 끼쳤어요
They really were very good indeed.
정말 잘하더군요
And so with that, I have to bring up the final slide.
이제 마지막 슬라이드를 불러올게요
Congratulations.
축하해요
I hope that you're proud of what you've accomplished.
당신이 이룬 성과에 자부심을 느끼길 바라요
I hope you do feel that sense that you have now reached an advanced point in your learning.
여러분이 이제 학습의 수준에 도달했다고 느끼길 바라요
You have got to the summit of the mountain.
산 정상에 올라야 해요
I'm so, so very happy.
정말 행복해요
And I hope, I really, really hope that you're able to take this and use it in your day job, in your
진심으로 바라건대 이 경험을 본업과 경력에 활용해서 앞으로 나아가길
career to move forwards.
바라요
And I very much want to hear all about it.
전부 다 듣고 싶어요
So do stay in touch.
계속 연락해요
Thank you once again.
다시 한번 고마워요
And a huge congratulations.
그리고 정말 축하해요